The next דף daf today we're on מ"ה עמוד ב' Mem Hey
amud bet and it's I mean today's דף daf is מ"ו Mem
Vav 46 but we're a little behind so we pick up מ"ה
עמוד ב' Mem Hey amud bet six lines down in the wide
lines to the two dots נשבר השדרה. Nishbar hashidra. Okay so we
are dealing now with the we're going through the various טריפות. trefot.
We dealt with the heart yesterday and now we're dealing with the
breaking of the spine is broken and as the משנה mishna continues
it says the spine and the spinal cord and the גמרא Gemara
understands that it is the spinal cord which is the the key
here. So let's take a look. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan.
Okay so is the spine broken to get to the spinal cord?
Yes. Yes. So in which case theoretically if the if the spine
is not broken but the spinal cord is broken?
Correct. It really the spine really the spine doesn't matter it's really
all about the spinal cord. Okay so let's take a look. תנו
רבנן. Tanu rabanan. חוט השדרה שנפסק דרובו. Chut hashidra shenipsak derubo. So
you see right here it starts with the spinal cord. If the
spinal cord the majority of it is cut. That that's a טריפה.
trefa. דברי רבי. Divrei Rebbi. That's what Rabbi says. רבי יעקב אומר
Rabbi Yaakov omer אפילו ניקב afilu nikav even a hole in the
spinal cord. הא רבי כרבי יעקב. Ha Rebbi k'Rebbi Yaakov. So interestingly
Rabbi himself when a case came in front of him ruled like
Rabbi Yaakov to be strict which is not what's recorded in our
משנה. mishna. Our משנה mishna he has his own position. So אמר
רב הונא. Amar Rav Huna. So Rav Huna says אין הלכה כרבי
יעקב. ein halacha k'Rabbi Yaakov. We don't rule like Rabbi Yaakov. Again
quite fascinating because normally we say you know מעשה רב maaseh rav
how somebody פסק-ed pasken more dictate than a theoretical פסק psak but
here based on the משנה mishna we are פוסק-ing pasken like Rabbi's
own or own original position.
Why would Rabbi hold by his own original?
Yeah it is quite strange. I do not know the answer. You
know I I would say just in a moment of reflection that
what is interesting is you have so many not only discussions but
actual narratives of people in the process of פסק psak that you
have in this פרק perek that you do not have in so
many other areas. You know this case came before him he did
this he sent it to so-and-so he he said this way but
then when a case came he ruled that way. So you know
it is interesting the intersection here of this being the traditional מסכת
masechet learned for for סמיכה semicha and how much the issue about
methodology of פסק psak and the actual practices of פסק psak you
have. So I don't know the exact answer about why here Rabbi
decided to be strict but anyway
the גמרא Gemara interestingly rejects that.
So let's so yeah let's go on. I would say by the
way I'll make another brief comment about this which is is that
you know with all of these debates you can't really even understand
how people are debating anything unless there's a principle at stake. So
the whole position that טריפה חיה treifa chaya that a טריפה treifa
can live
is you know is hard basically seems completely ignored by the entire
פרק perek because you know very often they're explicitly debating whether or
not the animal can live with this problem and even if they
weren't explicitly debating it there has to be some principle at stake
you know for to to understand these debates. So it's very hard
to understand you know any any traction to that position of טריפה
חיה. treifa chaya. All right let's continue.
Otherwise right? Well yeah that's also a problem of course is that
with the spinal cord why is that a טריפה trefa that really
would only lead to paralysis it would not lead to death. So
I I don't know the answer to that either once having mentioned
that problem that we are dealing presumably with the principle of טריפה
אינה חיה. treifa eina chaya.
Oh so I mean the the the paralyzed animal's not a טריפה?
trefa?
Well
I suppose that's true but if the owner if the owner feeds
it if we're dealing with a domesticated animal you know are we
talking about what lives in the wild? You know I don't know
how about an animal with broken legs? It's not really isn't really
that much different than paralyzed? I mean can it chew? Presumably it's
not paralyzed from the neck up. So I don't know I really
don't know the answer to that. Okay וכמה רובו. V'kama rubo. Now
how much is a majority? Again we had that question before when
we dealt with a number of different things what constitutes a majority
like when we dealt with the trachea so let's take a look.
So רב אמר רוב עורו. Rav amar rov oro. Majority of its
skin ואמרי לה רוב
מוחו. v'amrei leh rov mocho. Majority of its marrow. Now what do
we mean by marrow? So apparently I mean the way this is
I had to I looked up yesterday on Wikipedia
you know the spinal cord the actual nerve is extremely thin I
think it might even be microscopic I don't know about that but
anyway but what you have with the spinal cord is you have
three layers of different skin that are around the nerve. You've got
an outer protective layers then a gap and an inner layer which
is somewhat like of a web-like structure and then a gap and
then the dura mater which is the and that we're which is
directly which adheres directly to the actual nerve and is very thin.
So the question here about the מוח moach is referring to some
of this inner contents of the actual. spinal cord. I mean מוחו
mocho normally means marrow, and as far as I know it doesn't
have a marrow-like appearance, but it basically means the inner content. So,
so, so רש"י Rashi describes—so again, I don't know which of these
layers it's referring to as the מוח, moach, whether it's referring to
the dura mater is most likely or the second layer, but the
first opinion says you're cutting the outer, at least let's say the
outer layer of the skin, the first layer of the spinal cord.
The other opinion says it's not enough that you cut through the
first layer of spinal cord, you have actually cut into the majority
of the מוח. moach. So again, the מוח moach either means the
second protective layer of skin or it might mean the dura mater,
but you actually have to cut the majority of that in half
and it's not enough the outer layer, which if you're cutting actually
the majority of the dura mater, then you're cutting the nerve itself.
Otherwise, you know, you could understand the other position that if you
cut the outer layer, eventually it'll lead to a breaking of the
nerve, but the nerve itself would not have been cut. Okay, so
that's the debate here.
So again, it speaks about marrow as if it were in a
bone; it's not exactly that, but there is but it is somewhat
like that. Okay, so now let's continue where this goes in the
גמרא. Gemara.
So let's take a look. רבא רבא אמר ליה רוב מוחו מן
דאמר רוב מוחו. Rava Rava amar lei rov mocho man damar rov
mocho. If you say the majority of the marrow, quote unquote, כל
שכן רוב עורו, kol sheken rov oro, certainly the majority of the
skin. Now that wouldn't have occurred to us; the majority of the
marrow you're getting closer to the heart of it, but the גמרא
Gemara understands that, well, maybe you know, if it's if even the
marrow's a problem, even though the skin is still there protecting it,
somehow you manage to cut the majority of the marrow without the
majority of the skin, so the גמרא Gemara assumes that the majority
of the skin protecting it would mean it has a greater survival
chance. So if the marrow is enough, certainly if you cut the
outer skin it's going to be a problem because that will ultimately
lead to the entire snapping of the cord.
So the גמרא Gemara so that, again, for us that's a little
surprising, but that's the way the גמרא Gemara says it. למאן דאמר
רוב עורו, Leman damar rov oro, but if you say the majority
of the outer layer of skin, רוב מוחו מאי, rov mocho mai,
what if it were to just the majority of the of the
marrow? Now presumably, obviously you can't say that that would be a
טריפה treifa because then they wouldn't be debating. So let's take a
look. תא שמע, Ta shema, come and hear, דאמר נבלי אמר רב
הונא רובו שאמרו רוב עורו. de'amar Nivali amar Rav Huna rubo she'amru
rov oro. The
majority means the majority of the skin of the spinal cord. מוח
זה לא מעלה ולא מוריד, Moach zeh lo maaleh velo morid, the
actual מוח moach doesn't matter whether that is cut or not.
Again, you know, I don't know the science of the גמרא. Gemara.
It's possible that the גמרא Gemara understood sort of like a bone
where the bone is really what matters, that's what gives structure to
the, you know, and the marrow is not really needed for the
functionality of the bone. I mean, the marrow does its own thing,
but it's not needed for the functionality of the bone. So the
גמרא Gemara might have understood similarly that the עור or is what
really does the function of the spinal cord and this other inner
stuff is not really doing the function. But in reality, the inner
stuff in the spinal cord is protecting the nerve itself. So the
only way I suppose to explain this is, as I said, is
that is that it understands that as long as the skin is
intact it will be able to to somehow recover. Although the phrase,
I don't know, you know, the מוח moach doesn't make any bit
of a difference seems a little extreme.
Okay, so so we asked this question once or twice before, you
know, now that we—Yeah,
so we said that, you know, already by טריפות, treifas, you know,
we're going to see it in the גמרא Gemara and already in
the רמב"ם Rambam and very early on it was dealt with, which
is we don't play around with what we get from חז"ל. Chazal.
You know, how to explain that in terms of general questions about
theory of הלכה halacha and so on, obviously you know it's not
so clear. הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha leMoshe miSinai would help if it
weren't that everything here is being debated, so it's a little hard
to say that every detail is הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha leMoshe miSinai.
Presumably, the other part of the answer has to do with the
way הלכה halacha is crystallized in the גמרא Gemara and canonized in
the גמרא Gemara somehow becomes, you know, definitive. But then that raises
questions about is that by all things, just by טריפות, treifas, is
there no possibility about how הלכה halacha continues to evolve? So that's
really a שיעור shiur for itself, but yes, these are serious questions.
Maybe we'll have time at the end and we'll do a separate
שיעור shiur on, you know, some of the implications of all of
this. So let's take a look as the גמרא Gemara continues.
Okay. אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי,
Amar Rabbah bar bar Chana
amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, נתמרח פסול, nitmare'ach pasul, נתמסמס פסול. nitmasmes
pasul.
So what if the inside of the מוח moach is not cut,
but it is somehow dissolved? So these two things refer to different
types of dissolving.
נתמרח Nitmare'ach means that it's sort of like it's it's dissolved, it's
like water רש"י Rashi says, and the other one נתמסמס nitmasmes is
a little bit less, but it's not exactly the same. It's sort
of like it's, you know, it's like jelly, maybe might be a
good way, or soft but not liquefied. Okay, so he says those
two, that's essentially the same as the מוח moach being cut and
it is invalid if the inside— liquefied and you know again as
we know the inside is what matters more. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says like this: איזהו המרמצץ ואיזהו הממסמס, המרמצץ כל שנשפך
כקיתון *Eizehu hamramtses ve'eizehu hamemasmes, hamramtses kol shenishpach k'kito*. So המרמצץ *hamramtses*
means that it would spill out like a pitcher, meaning the inside
is completely liquefied, if you were to cut it open the insides
would spill out. הממסמס כל שאינו יכול לעמוד *Hamemasmes kol she'eino yachol
la'amod*. If the cord cannot stand, meaning it's you know the inside
is jellied, it doesn't have its stiffness, so if you were to
hold the cord in your hand it would flop over, it does
not have its rigidity. Okay, so בעי רב ירמיה *Ba'ei Rav Yirmiya*,
אינו יכול לעמוד מפני כובדו מאי *eino yachol la'amod mipnei kovedo mai*?
Let's say it can't stand because it's a very it's somehow it's
heavy, so maybe it does have a certain amount of rigidity but
it's just still somewhat top heavy and that makes it flop over.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says תיקו teiku. *teiku*, that we don't
know. Okay, so there's different versions about the insides being destroyed. בי
רב אמרי Amri, *Bei Rav amri*, in the house of רב *Rav*
they say, נתמסמסה פסול *nitmasmesa pasul*, נתמסמסה *nitmasmesa* פסול *pasul* like we
said, but נתמזמזה כשר Kasher. *nitmazmeza kasher*. But this other thing which
is even less than that, נתמזמזה *nitmazmeza* is כשר *kasher*. Now what
does this נתמזמזה *nitmazmeza* mean? We don't exactly know,
but רש״י Rashi *Rashi* basically says it means that some of the
inner, some of the מוח *moach* again, some of that inner part
of it has you know came out, but it hasn't been cut
and it hasn't been liquefied. Okay, but some of the inner content
has been removed, so that will still be כשר *kasher*. So now
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says מיתיבי *meitivei*, it brings a ברייתא Braisa,
*braita*, תוספתא *Tosefta*, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon בן אלעזר אומר omer, *Rabbi
Shimon ben Elazar omer*, בהמה שנתמזמז מוחה טריפה Treifa. *behema shenitmazmeiz mocha
treifa*. An animal that the מוח *moach*, again presumably now again מוח
*mocha* could mean the brain, you know, it's a little bit unclear
what the מוח *moach* means here, we're choosing to read it
as, you know, that it means the marrow of the spinal cord,
again you know simply the word מוח *moach* by itself could mean
the brain and we'll see a story in a minute, but anyway
here we're choosing to read it in our context. So if this
if this marrow has been נתמזמז *nitmazmeiz* somehow a little bit you
know disrupted, it is פסול *pasul*, it is a טריפה tereifa, *treifa*.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says no, ההיא נתמסמס איתמר *hahi nitmasmes
itmar*, that's not the right גרסא *girsa*, the right גרסא *girsa* is
נתמסמס *nitmasmes*, which again means like jellied and only then is it
a problem. אייני *Aini*? Is that true? והא לוי הוה יתיב בבי
מסותא *veha
Levi hava yativ bebei masuta*, לוי *Levi* was in a bathhouse, חזיא
לההוא גברא *chaza le'hahu gavra*, he saw a man דטרייה לרישיה *detarya
lerishei*, that
he banged his head, he smacked his head, and אמר נתמזמז מוחא
דדין *amar nitmazmeiz mocha dedein*, this person's brains have נתמזמז *nitmazmeiz*, have
been smushed or
something, so you see that and presumably it means that I'm afraid
he's going to die, somehow we assume that was the context, so
you see that even if it's נתמזמז *nitmazmeiz* it's a problem. So
again, it's not exactly clear what נתמזמז *nitmazmeiz* means. It doesn't sound
like רש״י Rashi *Rashi* said before that it means some of it
left the body because how did that happen to his brains? But
okay, maybe it means got smashed but it's still not jellied. Anyway,
so you see that's a problem. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says אמר אביי Amar Abbaye. לא לומר שאינו מוליד
*amar Abaye lo lemar she'eino molid*, no, it means that now because
of this he won't be able to have children, but it doesn't
mean that he won't live. Now where did it, what's the relationship
to having children? So רש״י Rashi *Rashi* says that there, I mean
רש״י Rashi *Rashi* doesn't say there was a belief, רש״י Rashi *Rashi*
says it as a fact, but I'll say it's the belief, that
the spinal cord which runs down the body, when it gets to
the thigh area, it spreads and one of them enters into the
penis and actually affects virility, so that that's a shoot off of
the spinal cord. So therefore the, if if something happened to the
brain which relates to the spinal cord or whatever, this מוח *moach*,
that the effect won't necessarily be that he'll die because it wasn't
that radical but it does have the effect that he will no
longer be able to have children. Again though, interesting whether the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* is making a comparison between the מוח *moach* of the
brain or it seems like we are talking about the מוח *moach*
of the spinal cord, not exactly clear. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* goes on, עד היכן heichan, *ad heichan*... Oh I should
say, I don't know if Rabbi Katz dealt this with you yesterday
but talking about the incorrect science, you know yesterday's גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
that spoke about three three branches that come off of the trachea,
one feeding into the heart and one feeding into the liver, you
know, that was obviously pretty shocking I imagine to most of you,
but that also did feed into, you know, rabbinic understanding or ancient
understanding that the heart is really not some, does not really, is
not really a pump of blood, but really is an organ that
assists in respiration, and therefore the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* understood that actually
one of the one of the tubes of the trachea feeds into
the heart. It's also relevant in understanding גמרות Gemoras *Gemarot* that are
sometimes quoted or ראשונים Rishonim *Rishonim* that are quoted to try to
argue for the importance of circulation as part of a definition of
death or life because actually in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s understanding the
heart is much more about respiration than it is about circulation. Okay,
that was a little comment on yesterday. yesterday's גמרא. Gemara Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara continues.
Okay, אמר אביי. Oh, I thought we just did that. אמר רב,
Amar Rav, רב דימי בר יצחק הוי קא בעי למיזל לבי חוזאי.
Rav Dimi bar Yitzchak hava ka ba'ei lemeizal leBe Khuzai. רב דימי
בר יצחק Rav Dimi bar Yitzchak was going to go to בי
חוזאי, Be Khuzai, which was some district there in...
Oh, I'm sorry, thank you very much, I skipped a line. אמר
יהודה אמר שמואל, Amar Yehuda amar Shmuel, עד בין הפרשיות. ad bein
haparshiyot. I'm sorry, היכן, let's start from the beginning of the line.
היכן חוט השדרה? Heichan chut hashidra? To where does the spinal cord
go that it's being cut is a problem? So, especially since now
we implicitly said that part of it feeds into other parts of
the body. So where does it go till? So, and as we
know of course, the spines and the nerves break off afterwards, and
it's not as critical as it gets lower down. So until where
does it go? So, so where were we? So אמר רב יהודה
אמר שמואל עד בין הפרשיות, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel ad bein
haparshiyot, till the בין הפרשיות. bein haparshiyot. Now רש״י Rashi has three
explanations what בין הפרשיות bein haparshiyot means. I'm going to say the
more simpler one, which is that it goes if you look at
a, I don't know if you have a picture of a cow
in front of you, but after the major ribcage, there are small
little ribs that continue down the backbone. And רש״י Rashi basically says
that בין הפרשיות bein haparshiyot is that area, the area beyond the
ribcage where you have these smaller little ribs and the בין הפרשיות
bein haparshiyot is like the spacing between those little ribs. Okay, we'll
talk about exactly where in that section in a minute. Okay, so
now we have a story. רב דימי בר יצחק Rav Dimi bar
Yitzchak הוי קא בעי למיזל לבי חוזאי. hava ka ba'ei lemeizal leBe
Khuzai. He wanted to go to בי חוזאי, Be Khuzai, which was
some district in בבל. Bavel. אתא לקמיה דרב יהודה. Ata lekaimei deRav
Yehuda. He came to רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, maybe to ask permission
for him to leave. So אמר ליה, amar lei, so before רב
דימי בר יצחק Rav Dimi bar Yitzchak left, רב יהודה Rav Yehuda
said to him, לחוי לי מר בין הפרשיות היכא. lechevi li mar
bein haparshiyot heicha. Show me where you're going to leave, show me
where I'm in the middle of learning טרפות, treifot, show me where
this area of בין הפרשיות bein haparshiyot is. אמר ליה אייתי לי
גדי ואחוי לך. Amar lei aiti li gedi ve'achvi lach.
Go bring me a goat and I will show you. Presumably this
means a slaughtered goat, at least that's the way רש״י Rashi says.
אייתי ליה גדי
שמינא, Aiti lei gedi shamina, brought him a fat goat. אמר ליה
בליע טפי. Amar lei bliya tefei.
Oh, it's too absorbed, it's too fatty. I can't exactly identify for
you the exact place. ולא ידיע, Velo yediya,
and it's hard to be known, it's hard to identify. So רש״י
Rashi says, it means that you can't see it from the outside,
maybe you'd have to dissect it first, but just looking at the
animal simply like this, it's hard to see. Okay, אייתי ליה כחוש,
aiti lei kachush, so they brought him a skinny goat. אמר ליה
בלית טפי. Amar lei belit tefei. It's too protruding. Now what does
it mean it's too protruding?
Why should that be a problem? ולא ידיע, Velo yediya, and it
can't be known. So what does רש״י Rashi say it means? רש״י
says that the hip bone is protruding too much and it's hiding
exactly the location. So again, I have no idea, not having ever
looked at dissected an animal and tried to identify these locations, how
this is possible. In another possible interpretation רש״י says that the animal
was still alive when he was trying to identify it, which obviously
makes more sense. But anyway he said, no, I'm sorry, it's too
fat, it's too skinny, I can't exactly show you. So אמר ליה
תא אגמרך גמרא. Amar lei ta agmerach gemara. Come so, so he
said to him, come let me teach you, so this is what
רב יהודה Rav Yehuda said to him. Now again, the גמרא Gemara
doesn't say this, but I'm wondering if this is a little bit
of a way of רב יהודה Rav Yehuda saying to him, hey,
before you decide that you're done learning and you want to go
somewhere else, whether on vacation, ha-ha, or to learn somewhere else, wherever
you're going, if you haven't passed this test, if you can't show
me where it is, I think you need to spend a little
bit more time learning from me. So that's my read of the
subtext. So then רב יהודה Rav Yehuda says to him, because remember
before we had the teaching of רב יהודה אמר שמואל. Rav Yehuda
amar Shmuel. So אמר ליה תא אגמרך גמרא. Amar lei ta agmerach
gemara. Let me teach you a tradition. And here's the tradition I
know. הכי אמר שמואל, Hachi amar Shmuel, this is what שמואל Shmuel
says. עד אחת טרפה, Ad achat treifa, until the first one it's
a טרפה. treifa. שלישית כשירה, Shlishit kesheira, if it's by the third
one it's a כשירה. kesheira. שנייה איני יודע, Shniya eini yodeya, by
the second I don't know. So what is this first, second, and
third? So again, there's a lot of different possible interpretations. רש״י gives
three. The one רש״י is happiest with is the first little rib,
minor rib, that's beyond the ribcage. That when the spinal cord gets
to that point where the two little bones split off for that
little rib, so up to there it's still the spinal cord. By
the time it gets to the third little rib, then it's considered
בין הפרשיות bein haparshiyot and it's not the spinal cord. And in
the middle section, including the second rib, I guess anywhere between after
the first and until the third, because these are not directly sequential,
there's space between them, that's not clear whether that's still considered the
spinal cord or not. Okay, and now the גמרא Gemara is going
to try to be a little bit more precise. So let's take
a look. בעי רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע, Ba'ei Rav Huna brei
deRav Yehoshua, רב הונא Rav Huna the son of רב יהושע Rav
Yehoshua asked on דף מ״ה עמוד א, daf mem hei amud aleph,
עד ועד בכלל או דילמא עד ולא עד בכלל. ad ve'ad bichlal
o dilma ad velo ad bichlal. When you say until the first
one... do you mean until and including or not including? Now of
course it's a funny question because since anywhere until the third, it's
at least a ספק טרפה, safek treifa, you wonder why this really
matters to know that it's a ודאי טרפה vadai treifa or not,
but nevertheless this is a question that was asked. So does that
include the actual, right, when it gets up to, imagine again you
know if you think about how a rib cage looks or after
you're looking at a picture, you know the bones separate off when
it gets to the first point which is called בין הפרשיות bein
haparshiyot because you know that's where they separate off, they separate where
it gets to this these like smaller ribs down the down the
spinal cord. So does that include the space of where those bones
separate off or is that included in where it's a ודאי טרפה
vadai treifa or is it only a ודאי טרפה vadai treifa till
it gets to those little bones? But that beyond that point it's
already a ספק. safek. So that's the question. Again why it matters
so much is a little unclear. So בעי רב פפא, Ba'ei Rav
Pappa, Rav Pappa asked, אם תמצי לומר עד ולא עד בכלל, im
timtzi lomar ad v'lo ad bichlal, if you say that it doesn't
include the area of the bones themselves, you know again not the
bones, the bones are not part of the of the don't have
the spinal cord in it, but where the spine, you know where
the bones break off from the spine, so פי פרשה מהו? pi
parasha mahu? What if it's right by the opening of that space?
So in the actual middle of that space where the bones are
separating off to the two sides even if that's not included, what
if it's right by where that space begins? So now we're talking
about like I don't know a centimeter that we're asking about. That's
one question. בעי רבי ירמיה, Ba'ei Rabbi Yirmeya, Rabbi Yirmeya asked a
question on the other side, אם תמצי לומר עד ועד בכלל, im
timtzi lomar ad v'ad bichlal, if it includes that space where the
spine goes between the two bones, those little bones, so פרשה עצמה
מהו? parasha atzma mahu? What about the separation itself? What does this
mean? So again with the interpretation of רש"י Rashi that we're going
by, it means the bones themselves, those bones that separate off, what
if they were to break? Now of course as we've just been
saying that even the breaking of the spinal of the spine doesn't
matter until you break the spinal cord. So the גמרא Gemara is
going to very quickly reject that those bones should matter. תא שמע,
Ta shema, come and hear, הפרשה כדון כבשר. haparasha kidon k'basar.
So the separation itself that's treated like flesh, meaning it's nothing, it's
like a piece of a normal piece of meat broke, it has
no significance. מאי לאו פרשה ראשונה? Mai lav parasha rishona? Oh, I'm
sorry but first the I'm sorry I jumped ahead. First the גמרא
Gemara says, does that not mean that it's treated I'm sorry, no,
I'm sorry I was right. Does that not mean even in this
first space where the you know this first little mini rib mini
mini rib and that it's when the bones themselves break it's not
a problem, פרשה ראשונה ושניה? parasha rishona u'shniya? So the גמרא Gemara
says לא שלישית, lo, shlishit, no, it means the third one, that
that's treated like that's like flesh because the third one itself even
if the spine broke it would not be an issue, but we
don't know what the story is when when these bones break. Now
that's one way רש"י Rashi reads it, again it's a little bit
funny as I said because the גמרא Gemara even doesn't even resolve
it what the story is when those little little ribs break and
we know that the what really matters is the spinal cord and
not the spine itself. So another explanation רש"י Rashi has about the
פרשה עצמה parasha atzma is not the is not the ribs that
separate off from this what we call בין הפרשיות, bein haparshiyot, but
it's actually the space between those two you know you know those
two points where the ribs separate from. So right, we're talking about
the basic rib cage has completed, if you continue looking down the
spinal cord there are like mini ribs separating off as it continues
down and we're talking about the point, whatever that's called, the nexus
but whatever it is, anyway those points where those mini ribs separate
off, we're talking about first, second, and third. So the פרשה עצמה
parasha atzma can mean the space between one and two and the
space between two and three and that's a better question. So you
say number one itself is considered ודאי טרפה, vadai treifa, number three
itself is considered ודאי כשרה, vadai k'shaira, what about the space between
and number two is ספק. safek. Well what about the space between
one and two? If one is ודאי vadai and two is ספק,
safek, is the space between one and two, is that also ודאי
vadai or is that included with number two to be a ספק?
safek? That question makes a lot more sense. So and so the
actual bones?
What?
No, yeah, the actual spinal cord, the spinal, I'm not not the
spinal cord, the spine itself right? Or the spinal cord because that's
really what matters. So if when the spine a spinal the spinal
cord itself is at point one where the bones separate off that's
ודאי טרפה vadai treifa and when it's at point two when it
breaks there it's ודאי כשרה, vadai k'shaira, no it's ספק, safek, what
about where the spinal cord goes between point one and two? Right,
cause there's a gap between where those little ribs break off from.
So what's the story with that? That makes a lot more sense
that that's a serious question. Okay, so
so and so that's where the גמרא Gemara has the question about
what that status would be. Okay, so we have all these questions
about where how far down does it go. Now the גמרא Gemara
continues, בעוף, B'ofa, what about the story by a bird, how far
down does the spinal cord go that it matters? רבי ינאי אומר
למטה מן האגפיים, Rabbi Yannai omer l'mata min ha'agapayim, underneath the wings.
ריש לקיש אמר *Reish Lakish amar* עד בין האגפיים *ad bein ha'agapayim*,
no, until the wings begin. So that's a pretty huge difference. Is
it, you know, is it from where the wings start, it's no
longer טריפה tereifa *treifa*? We're talking about, by the way, the ability
to survive in the wild. I imagine that if, again, I don't
know what would happen, but I imagine if it got cut where
the wings
are already, in that space where the wings are connected, that it
probably would lose the ability to fly, I mean it probably would
be paralyzed in its wings, I don't know. But anyway, one says
it's a problem only until the wings begin, and the other says
it's a problem all throughout where the wings are attached, until the
bottom of the wings. תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* wants to know, does the
bottom of the wings mean the bottom of where the wings are
attached to the body, which is what I would assume, or the
bottom of where the wings lie against the body, which would be
even much lower? Okay, so אמר עולא *amar Ulla*. So עולא *Ulla*
says, הוי קמינא קמי דרב פזי *havi kamina kamei deRav Pazzi*, I
was in front of רב פזי *Rav Pazzi*, ואייתו לקמיה עופא *va'aisu
lekamei ofa*, they brought in front of him a bird that had
a question, presumably if it was a טריפה treifa *treifa* or not,
ובדיק עד בין האגפיים *u'badik ad bein ha'agapayim*, he was checking for
a severing until between the wings, he got from the neck till
the space right where the wings begin, ושלח ליה דבי נשיא *veshalach
lei debei nesia*, then there was a messenger came from the house
of the נשיא *Nasi*, וקם ואזיל *vekama ve'azil*, and he went to
go respond to the call that he was being called to the
נשיא *Nasi*'s house, and he stopped checking the bird. Now he never
explicitly gave a פסק *psak*, he just ran to go to the
נשיא *Nasi*, ולא ידנא אם משום דלא צריך מדק טפי *vilo yadanah
im mishum d'lo tzarich midak tfei*, is it because he was done
checking and you don't have to check after the wings begin, you
don't care about the space between the wings and therefore he basically
said it was כשר *kosher*, או משום כבוד נשיא *o mishum kavod
nesia*, no, it's because if you're called by the נשיא *Nasi*, you
drop what you're doing and you go and you answer the call
and he wasn't done checking and when he would come back he
would finish checking, so I don't know how to interpret it. Now
what I will say is interesting about this story is, you know,
we've raised the question a number of times: do you have to
check for all of the things every time you open up an
animal? And we said, no, no, only for the ones that are
considered common, basically the problems of the lungs, which we'll get to
today. But here, if he was checking, it's not like before where
there was a cut in the trachea and you were checking to
see how deep it was. If he's checking, presumably we don't know
that there's a cut, because if you know that there's a cut,
you know exactly where the cut is. So it sounds like you
don't know that there was a cut and he was just checking
to see if there was a cut. So that is interesting in
terms of that question about what.
Maybe he fell off a roof and maybe he wasn't flapping his
wings.
Oh, that's an interesting point. Ah, okay, I stand corrected. So that's
interesting. So there was a reason for him to suspect. Maybe that's
the case. Okay. Good. So that is the end of the spinal
cord. And again, of course, the question about why the spinal cord
matters if it only makes the animal paralyzed is never really answered.
Okay. Now the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* continues. ניטל הכבד *nital hakaved*, so
if the liver is removed and none remains, you'll remember that a
later משנה Mishna, *Mishnah* says you need a כזית kezayis. *kezayit*'s worth
to remain. So now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to deal
with that. Let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
like this, הנישתייר ממנו כלום *hanishtayer mimenu klum*, the implication of our
משנה Mishna. *Mishnah* is that if a little bit of the liver
remains, כשרה keshera, *kesheira*, it's כשר *kosher*, even if it's not a
כזית kezayis *kezayit*. והתנן *vehatnan*, but a later משנה *Mishnah* says where
we're
talking about what is כשר *kasher*, it says ניטל הכבד ונשתייר ממנו
כזית kezayis כשרה keshera, *nital hakaved venishtayer mimenu kezayit kesheira*, if the
liver is removed and a כזית kezayis *kezayit* remains. So make up
your mind, do you need a כזית kezayis *kezayit* or only a
little bit? These נשתיירות *nishrayot* contradict themselves. So אמר רב יוסף Rav
Yosef. לא קשיא *amar Rav Yosef lo kashya*, it's not difficult. הא
רבי חייא Rebbi Chiya הא רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon, בר רבי *ha
Rabbi Chiyya ha Rabbi Shimon bar Rabbi*. It's, I mean it is
difficult, but it's basically two different opinions. One is רבי חייא Rebbi
Chiya *Rabbi Chiyya* and one is רבי שמעון בר רבי *Rabbi Shimon
bar Rabbi*. So רבי חייא *Rabbi Chiyya* was רבי *Rabbi*'s nephew I
think, or whatever, anyway, but he was and רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*
was רבי *Rabbi*'s son. So כי הא דרבי חייא *ki ha deRabbi
Chiyya*, and now we have an interesting little story about their eating
habits when it came to eating liver. How did they differ? רבי
חייא זריק ליה *Rabbi Chiyya zorik lei*. רבי חייא *Rabbi Chiyya* just
threw out the liver. He did not eat the liver.
No chopped liver for him. רבי שמעון בר רבי מטביל ליה *Rabbi
Shimon bar Rabbi matbil lei*. רבי שמעון בר רבי *Rabbi Shimon bar
Rabbi* would dip the liver like you dip things that you eat
them, he would eat this as a maybe as a little as
an appetizer. Okay, so what is it? וסימנך *vesimanach*, and the way
you can remember who did what, one minute. עשירים מקמצין *ashirim mekamtzin*,
rich people are cheap. So rich people are stingy. So basically רבי
שמעון בר רבי *Rabbi Shimon bar Rabbi*, right, he was a son
of רבי *Rabbi*, he was from the נשיא *Nasi*'s house, so he
was very wealthy, so he didn't want to waste any, you know,
how do you think I got to be wealthy, by not wasting
anything? So he kept the
liver. רבי חייא *Rabbi Chiyya* who was not wealthy, he didn't care
for the liver. Okay, so now that you'll remember who said what.
Now what does that tell you about whether it's a טריפה treifa,
*treifa* or not? So רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says, well if you'll remember
we said before that things that are vital parts of the life
of the animal are also seen as being healthy, like the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* spoke before about how, you know, as soon as you
שחט *shecht* the animal while it's still alive to rip out a
piece of meat and it has that life force in it and
that'll give you. And it'll be healthy. So therefore, so if you
ate the liver, it shows that you felt that it was important
as the life force of the animal. So therefore, רבי שמעון ברבי,
Rabbi Shimon bar Rabbi. who ate the liver, obviously felt it was
a more vital part of the animal, and he would have demanded
a כזית. kezayis רבי חייא throughout the liver, he obviously did not
feel that it was such a vital life force of the animal
or else he would have eaten it just for health reasons if
nothing else. And רש"י Rashi even goes so far to say that
the entire reason he would need the משהו mashehu is not even
to do the function of the liver, but that the משהו mashehu
should cover up where the liver connects to the gallbladder and should
not expose, you know, make a hole in the gallbladder. So which
is interesting.
But so the way רש"י Rashi reads it is really a question,
does the liver really do any function or not, where רבי חייא
is completely denying the importance of the liver. Okay, the גמרא Gemara
before indicated by the way that we rule a כזית kezayis and
that's how the גמרא Gemara is going to continue here as well.
So let's take a look.
So we don't know at the end of the הלכה, Halacha, it
must be the גמרא Gemara continues. Right, so that's why I just
said, the גמרא Gemara before indicated by רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan had
a quote in the name of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan a day
or two ago that said a כזית kezayis and the גמרא Gemara
here is going to speak about a כזית kezayis. as well, so
it seems very clearly that we rule like, you know, the second
משנה, which now we're being told is רבי שמעון ברבי. So let's
take a look. Okay, ההוא פולמסא דאתא לפומבדיתא. hahu pulmasa de'asa le'Pumbedisa.
Certain army troop came to Pumbedisa. You might be familiar with the
word פולמסא pulmasa from the English word polemic, which comes from the
Greek word polemos, which basically means battle or war. So here it
means, the גמרא Gemara talks, the גמרא Gemara in סוטה Sotah talks
about the battles of Hadrian, פולמסא. pulmasa. Anyway, so here it's an
army troop, they came to Pumbedisa. And basically the Jews were afraid
that they were going to be drafted or,
so let's take a look, so ערקו, arku, where are we, or
drafted or other things, pressed into service in some way.
So ערקו רבה ורב יוסף. arku Rabba ve'Rav Yosef. So רבה ורב
יוסף Rabba ve'Rav Yosef ran away so as not to somehow be,
you know, be injured or
otherwise affected by this army troop. פגע בהו רבי זירא. paga behu
Rabbi Zeira. רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira bumped into them. Now רבי זירא
Rabbi Zeira happened to have connections with the government, so he was
able to move around more freely when these troops were there, he
did not have to worry.
אמר להו, amar lehu, he said to them, ערוקאי, arukai, deserters, runners
away, very nice for him to call them that given that he's
able to move around freely. Anyway,
כזית שאמרו במקום מרה. kezayis she'amru bimkom mara. You should know by
the way that when you know that when we speak about that
little כזית kezayis? of the liver, it has to be where the
gallbladder is, presumably to protect the gallbladder as well as do its
own function. ואפה בר אחוא אמר במקום שהיא חיה. Ve'Afah bar Ahva
amar bimkom shehi chayah. Where the animal lives, which is very interesting,
what is that supposed to mean? Let's just read what רב פפא's
Rav Pappa statement is and then we'll talk about it. אמר רב
פפא הלכך בעינן כזית במקום מרה ובעינן כזית במקום שהיא חיה. Amar
Rav Pappa hilkach ba'inan kezayis bimkom mara uba'inan kezayis bimkom shehi chayah.
Therefore, since we have these two different opinions, if we're going to
say a כזית kezayis is enough, you'll need it in both places
because we're not going to decide between the two opinions. Both where
the gallbladder is and where it lives. Now what does it mean
במקום שהיא חיה? bimkom shehi chayah? So רש"י Rashi says that he
says it seems that means that where it sort of is two
opinions, one is either it's the lobe of the liver, if you
look at a picture you'll see that the liver at one point
has like a section of it that's almost like an ear flapping
over, or רש"י Rashi says it's where the liver is sort of
embedded between the kidneys. So he has those two explanations. Embedded where
it's sort of embedded in the body between the kidneys or underneath
the kidneys.
Okay, so let's take a look.
So the גמרא Gemara now continues, so you see therefore to play
it safe you need it in both places. בעי רבי ירמיה. ba'ei
Rabbi Yirmiyah. So רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiyah asked the following question. מלקט
מהו. milaket mahu. Let's say you don't have a כזית Kezayis all
exactly combined. It's like a little bit here, a little bit there.
Now presumably in the places you said you needed it, either by
the gallbladder by the kidneys, but it's not one כזית Kezayis in
one, you know, all in one unit, it's little bits here and
little bits there that combines to a כזית. Kezayis. What's that story?
כרצועה מהו. keritua mahu. What if it's stretched out like a long
thin string? So maybe they're all connected but they're again not sort
of, you know,
not nicely in a concentrated area.
So the גמרא Gemara doesn't have an answer to that. בעי רב
אשי, ba'ei Rav Ashi, כזית מרודד מהו. kezayis merudad mahu. What if
it's like a very thin and flattened כזית? Kezayis Meaning, yes, you
know, it covers, you know, imagine it like a thin film. So
is that enough to continue its function? Technically you have כזית but
there's no thickness to it. What's the story there? תיקו. So all
these the גמרא Gemara says we'll have to wait. So בעי מיניה
רב זריקא מרב אמי, Baei minei Rav Zerika me-Rav Ami, so רב
זריקא Rav Zerika asked from רב אמי, Rav Ami, נדלדלה כבד ומעורה
בטרפשיה מהו? Niddaldela kaved u-me'ura be-tarpesheih mahu?
Let's say the liver has been loosened, but it still is hanging
on or wrapped around with its membrane. What's the story? So presumably
it means that there even the entire liver, so there wouldn't even
be a כזית left, but it's not completely removed from the body,
somehow it is disconnected, you know, but it's still being kept in
its place by some surrounding ligaments or membranes. What's the story? So
אמר ליה, Amar leih, he said to him, דלדו זה לא ידענא
מהו. Dildoo zeh lo yadana mahu. I don't know what this. And
it does not mean I don't know, it sort of means like
sort of like the גמרא said before by מוח וזה איני יודע
מהו. Moach vezeh eini yodea mahu. You know, there's no significance to
that. I don't know what this, never heard of it before. Why
should it matter? Okay, as long as it's still there, who cares?
Who cares? אי למאן דאמר במקום מרה
האי איכא. Ei le-man de-amar bi-mekom marah hai ika. If you say
you need a כזית where there's the gallbladder, it's still there. אי
למאן דאמר במקום שהיא חיה האי איכא. Ei le-man de-amar bi-mekom she-hi
chaya hai ika. If you need it where it lives, again, whatever
that means, let's say the kidneys, it's still there. So who cares
if it's a little loosened, it's still right there. Okay. So that
is the end for the liver where basically as you see we
rule כזית. We had an interesting question about people's eating habits with
livers and the כזית has to be either with the gallbladder or
where it lives, which presumably means the kidneys. Now we get on
to the lungs. And this is going to be a very important
discussion because the lungs is the central place where we have issues
with טרפות, Treifos, because of concerns about סירכות. Sirchos. סירכות Sirchos are
adhesions. Again, I don't know if you have a picture book there.
If you have that, if you do have one of those picture
books, at least particularly Joe, Joe's nice glossy pictures, if you might
want to open to it, you'll see that they have a very
nice picture of what those adhesions look like, which connect the lungs
either to the inner ribcage or different lobes of the lungs to
one another. So these adhesions are an issue. By the way, the
whole word גלאט Glatt means smooth, means without adhesions. Now you're never
going to get a cow as far as I know that has
no adhesions in its lungs, but גלאט Glatt really is a different
degree, like you know, you only allow very sort of minor adhesions,
not major adhesions and so on. Why are adhesions a problem? It's
not exactly clear. Almost all the evidence points to the idea, which
is what רש״י says and there's a huge תוספות Tosafot we'll see
when we turn the page that discusses it, that an adhesion is
a sign that there used to be a hole and the adhesion
is covering it up. And that's why adhesions are a problem. Some
say תוספות Tosafos plays with the possibility that maybe there isn't a
hole yet, but the adhesion could cause a hole to be made
and maybe that creates טריפה. treifa. But we're going to bracket that.
We're assuming that an adhesion, the concern is, is that it's covering
up a hole in the lung. And that's why adhesions are problems
and גלאט Glatt means free of adhesions, but we will see that
there's some ways of getting out of it, and גלאט Glatt does
not mean completely free of adhesions, it just means free of...
No, can I shut you off for one second please?
Sure. Okay,
all right, so let's take a look now.
He had a question. Yeah. With the adhesions, did you say if
it had adhesions then it's not גלאט? Glatt? Correct.
גלאט Glatt means smooth. Now, but that's not really true because every
animal has adhesions in the lungs, but not... but it means how
much, what our sort of tolerance level is for adhesions, you know,
whether whether they peel off easily or don't peel off easily and
so on. Meaning the basic issue is going to be, as we'll
see, not... we'll get a hint of it today but we'll see
more tomorrow, is there a way of testing whether there's a hole
under the adhesion? Can you basically peel off the adhesion or and
put it in water and see if air bubbles come out and
so on? And maybe if you can see that there wasn't a
hole under the adhesion maybe it's still כשר. So גלאט Glatt really
means that it only has very thin adhesions that peel off easily
and not גלאט Glatt is that you'll sort of, you know, you'll
tolerate even thicker adhesions doing these types of tests. So we'll talk
more about the
details tomorrow, but in theory גלאט Glatt means smooth without adhesions, but
in practice it really just means that we have a lower tolerance
for these adhesions. I have a question about what happened before, but
like you know, if it was like right on the, whatever it
was, that case that was kind of plugging up a hole?
Right,
so we'll talk about that. So let's take... let's start reading the
גמרא, we'll start seeing those things, okay? So let's take a look.
And by the way, this is why the major thing that we
check is the lungs, because they're the ones that present the problems
most frequently. Okay, so הריאה שניקבה, Ha-reiah she-nikvah, the lung with a
hole. רב ושמואל ורב אסי, Rav u-Shmuel ve-Rav Assi, דאמרי דאמרי de-amri
de-amri both Rav Shmuel and Rav Assi say, קרומה עילאה. Kruma ila'ah.
Now, דאמרי לה de-amri lah קרומה תתאה. Kruma tata'ah. So first of
all the question is, what if it's the hole is, how far,
which is the hole piercing through? So some say it means this
outer קרומא, kruma, this outer, yeah, this outer layer, and some say
it means even the inner layer. So it's sort of like the
same debate that we had before about the membrane around the brain.
Here we're talking
about the different sort of layers of the lungs itself. So let's
take a look. אמר רב יוסף בר מיומי אמר רב נחמן וסימנך,
Amar Rav Yosef bar Miyumi Amar Rav Nachman v'simancha, the way to
remember or the way he actually פסקנס paskens is ככיתונא דורדא דמנחא
בי ריאה. ke-chituna de-varda de-mancha bei reiya. It's like a red cloak
that the lung is in. So because the closest sort of layer
to the lung itself, the membrane around the lung, is red. So
he's basically ruling that it's only a problem when the inner membrane
is pierced, and that's the one and it looks almost like a
membrane that
contains a red cloak around the lung, similar to the way the
גמרא before talked
about the little bag that surrounds the brain. But hold on one
minute, I just want to look at one thing in the משנה.
Yeah, so remember רבי שמעון says that the lung has to go
all the way into the area of the בית הסמפונות, Beit HaSimponot,
the place where the branches where it branches off, that a little
piercing is not enough. Now, even without רבי שמעון, you might have
imagined that it would have been enough to have pierced into that
you would have at least required it to have pierced into the
hollow of the lung, the same way you require it pierces into
the hollow of the heart, because here it never mentioned the membrane
around the lung. It did mention the membrane around the brain. But
nevertheless, at least the way this גמרא is these opinions are really
saying that it doesn't need to go through it to the hollow
of the lung, it's enough to pierce through the outer membrane or
at least the inner membrane of the lung and that already suffices.
Okay, so now the גמרא continues.
Okay. פשיטא אי נקיב עילאה ולא נקיב תתאה תתאה מגינת. Pshita i
nekiv ila'a v'lo nekiv tatta'a tatta'a maginat.
It's obvious that if the outer membrane was pierced and not the
inner one, that the inner one protects. I mean, it's not obvious,
but that's the way we just said, that we just ruled that
you need to have even the inner one, this red cloak as
it were, pierced through. Okay, that's clear. כדרבא, Ke-Rava, like רבא Rava
says. דאמר רבא, De-amar Rava, because רבא Rava says, האי ריאה דאגליד
דאתיא סומקא... Hai reiya de-iglid de-atya sumka...
if a lung is peeled and it looks like a red date,
so
again apparently this inner membrane is red. So if you peel the
entire outer membrane and it looks like a red date, כשרה, kosher
it's kosher. So even if the entire outer membrane is removed, it's
still kosher. That we accept because the inner membrane protects it. However,
נקיב תתאה ולא נקיב עילאה, nekiv tatta'a v'lo nekiv ila'a,
let's say the inner membrane is pierced but not the outer membrane,
מגין או לא מגין, magin o lo magin,
is the fact that the outer membrane is still there, is that
enough to protect it or not if the inner membrane has a
hole?
So פליגי בה רב אחא ורבינא. pligi bei Rav Acha u-Ravina. So
they debate. חד אמר לא מגין, chad amar lo magin, one
says it doesn't protect if the inner one is pierced, right? So
you never have this question, for example, by the brain. By the
brain we said it's the inner membrane, and we never said what
if it's just the inner and not the outer, because how would
that happen? But here you have the question what if it's just
the inner and not the outer? So חד אמר לא מגין, chad
amar lo magin, one says it does not protect the outer one,
וחד אמר מגין, v'chad amar magin, it does. והלכתא מגין, v'hilchata magin,
and the הלכה halacha is it does protect. So you need both
the inner and the outer one to be pierced. כדרב יוסף, ke-Rav
Yosef, like the story of רב יוסף. Rav Yosef דאמר רב יוסף,
de-amar Rav Yosef, רב יוסף says, האי ריאה דאוושא, hai reiya de-avsha,
if let's say a lung makes noise, meaning that you're blowing through
the lungs. This is a way to test for holes in the
lung. You take the lung out of the animal and you blow
into it like it's a balloon, and you hear a little shh,
like a little whistle, like air escaping. Okay, so now you've got
a hole. So what are you going to do? אי ידיענא היכא
אוושא, ei yadyana heicha avsha, if you know where you heard that
sound from, where that whistling from, מותבינן עלה גדפא או רוקא, motvinan
alei gadfa o roka, you put on that space, you can't see
a hole, but you put on that space a feather or some
spittle, או גילא, o gila, or a straw,
ואם מבעבעא טריפה, v'im meva'v'a tereifa, if it
flutters, as now you blow again, טריפה, treifa. then it's a טריפה
treifa? because then you know air is escaping to the outside. ואי
לא מבעבעא כשרה, v'ei lo meva'v'a keshera, and if it doesn't flutter
as you're blowing through it, כשרה, kesheira, it's kosher. Okay, now why
is there sound being made? We'll talk about that in a minute.
ואי לא ידיענא היכא אוושא, v'ei lo yadyana heicha avsha, if you
don't know where the sound is coming from. So how would you
test for a hole if you don't know where the sound is
coming from? Anybody? What would you do? Put it in water. מייתינן
מתיכלא דמיא, meisinei mitikla d'maya, you take a vessel filled with water,
פשורי, p'shurei, lukewarm water, ומותבינן ליה בגבה, umosvinan lei begaba, put it
in while it's blown up as a balloon, okay, בחמימי לא, bachamimei
lo, not in hot water, דכווצי, d'kvatzi, that would cause the hole
to shrink—not shrink, what's the word? Anyway, to compress, anyway, the area
around it, so it would hide the hole. בקרירי לא, bekarimei lo,
not in cold water, דטרשי, d'tarshei, it makes it hard and might
actually cause a hole to be created. אלא מותבינן בפשורי, ela mosvinan
bipshurei, you put it in lukewarm water, ונפקינן ליה, venafkinan lei, and
you blow it up. אם מבצבצא, im mivatzvetza, if now you get
little air bubbles, טריפה is טריפה, ואילו כשירה, v'ilo kashira, and if
not
it's
kosher. Now if
it's not—if air isn't escaping, what's making the sound? How could you
say it's כשירה? kashira? So here's how it's כשירה. kashira. תתאה אינקיב
עילאה לא אינקיב, tata inkiv ila lo inkiv, the reason it's making
the sound is because the outer membrane has been pierced, but the
inner membrane has not. So the air escapes from the inner thing,
and apparently there's a space—again, I didn't have a chance to look
this up, you might have pictures—but apparently there's a space between the
inner and the outer. So the air escapes
from the hollow of the
lung, it goes through the hole in the inner
membrane and it gets into the space between the inner and the
outer. So that's why you're hearing some sound, some air escaping, but
as long as it's not escaping till the outside through the outer
membrane, it's not a טריפה. So now what we're saying
is that there has to be a hole, it's just on the
out—is not enough, just on the inside is not enough, it has
to be on the in and the out, and presumably, although interestingly
this has not been said, and if you remember we had similar
questions about other things, presumably it has to be a continuous hole,
meaning, although maybe not, I don't know, maybe as long as the
air escapes through any hole. What if there's a hole in one
place in the lung on the inner wall and in a different
place on the lung on the outer wall? Right, that's not being
explicitly stated. We had those types of questions before. But here you
see that it has to be a hole that will let air
get from the inside of the lung all the way till the
outside. So what it sounds like is, and again, I don't have
the picture in front of me, I tried to look some of
this up on Wikipedia, is it sounds like we're not talking like
the two membranes around the brain, where you basically had the brain
and then you had something different which was a protective
membrane directly on it and another membrane that was closer to the
skull. Here it sounds like we're really talking about like two walls
of the lung itself, right, so that a hole in the inner
wall lets the air escape from the lung to the space between
the two walls, and a hole in the outer wall lets the
air escape to the outside. So it sounds like we're actually talking
about a double wall of the lung itself. Okay, and you need
the hole to be all the way through. And here we have
a great way of testing, you know,
if you have a doubt, if you heard air escape, how do
you test? And this issue about blowing up the lung and testing
it is going to be very relevant to issues about the adhesions
as well. All right, now let's take—now let's continue. So Zevid at
the last line: והאי דאוושא זיקא דביני ביני הוא, v'hai d'avsha zika
d'beini beini hu,
is the air between the inner and outer wall. Okay so now
the Gemara continues גופא, gufa, so let's take a look at this
position. אמר רבא, amar rava, האי ריאה דאיגליד כהימנא סומקא, hai reia
d'iglid k'hymna sumka,
if a lung was peeled, the outer wall was peeled away and
now it looks like a red date, כשירה, kashira, it's kosher because
as long as you have the inner wall it's okay. ואמר רבא,
v'amar rava, ריאה שהדימה מקצתה כשירה, reia she-hidima miktzata kashira,
if the lung is a little red—now why should that be a
problem? We just said red is okay. So here it doesn't mean
red because it's peeled, here it means red because it's been wounded.
It's like a—you know, what do you call it? Not a black
and blue mark, but what do you call it when somebody gets
a hit and it starts getting, you know, it starts darkening around
where it's hit? I mean, it is a black and blue mark,
but there's maybe a more specific term for that. Anyway, that's what
we're talking about, that
it's been wounded, not punctured, but the blood is collecting in that
spot and therefore it looks reddish. So it's collecting under the skin.
So therefore, so what's the story? Is that considered like a tear
or not? So here's what he says: שהדימה, she-hidima, it got red
as a result of a wound, מקצתה כשירה, miktzata kashira, if it's
only a part of it it's kosher, כולה טריפה, kula treifa, all
of it it's טריפה. אמר ליה רבינא לרבא, amar lei ravina l'rava,
מקצתה מאי טעמא, miktzata mai taama, why are you saying if it's
only a little bit it's not a טריפה? דהדר בריא, d'hadar barya,
it'll heal. כולה נמי הדר בריא, kula nami hadar barya,
even if it's all of it logically it should heal. Why? מי
לא תניא, mi lo tanya, we taught in the baraita, ושרץ הקוצים.
v'sharetz haktzavim. ושאר שקצים ורמשים עד שיצא מהם דם. v'shear shekatzim u-remashim
ad she-yeitzei mehem dam.
By שבת Shabbos
there is one of the מלאכות melachos of שבת Shabbos is being
מוציא דם, motzi dam, you know, wounding somebody and having blood or
not even wounding, even for health purposes, whatever, but anyway making blood
come out of a person or of an animal. Now let's say
you didn't actually make the blood come out, but you gave him
a smack and he got a black and blue mark and the
blood collated, you know, you broke blood vessels obviously and the blood
collected underneath the skin but didn't come out. So we would say
that that also would be a מלאכה melacha on שבת. Shabbos. Now
how about by animals? So the גמרא distinguishes between certain animals, you
know, large animals definitely. In terms of like more the rodents, so
it says the eight rodents that are mentioned in the תורה Torah
that cause טומאה, tumah, those are considered to have real skin and
if you wound them and you see redness then you've broken blood
vessels and it's collecting underneath the skin and that is a מלאכה,
melacha, it's like you caused the blood to come out. By the
other animals they don't have real skin, so unless you, you know,
I don't know what it considers it to be, but whatever, it's
not real skin as far as the גמרא is concerned and therefore
even if it gets red, presumably you did not really break any
blood vessels or it's not considered significant until the blood actually comes
out. Now why is all of this relevant? So let's take a
look. So it's relevant because he says look, so on the one
hand you see that if you consider the, you know, if you
consider the wound not significant and you're considering it to be sort
of like these other animals where redness doesn't really indicate a serious
breaking of blood vessels or whatever, then it shouldn't even matter even
if it was the entire, you know, lung, the same way, you
know, if you made these entire you know you caused wounds on
these entire animals, you wouldn't be מחלל שבת, mechallel Shabbos, you know,
if it's if it hasn't done anything you haven't done anything on
all of it. וכי תימא לשמונה שרצים מדמינן לה, v'chi teima l'shmonah
sheratzim medaminan lah, so let's say you say, oh I'm not comparing
it to those other animals, I'm comparing it to the eight rodents
where they have real skin and you really do break blood vessels
even, you know, even if the blood doesn't come out. So if
that's true, דתניא נצרר הדם אף על פי שלא יצא, de-tanya nitzrar
ha-dam af al pi she-lo yatza, if the blood collated even though
it did not come out, you've done a מלאכה, melacha, הכי אפילו
במקצתה נמי, hachi afilu be-miktzata nami, so if that's true then even
for even a small part of it. Meaning make up your mind,
you know, if if without the blood coming out it's something that
can heal, so why should it matter if it's on, you know,
let it be even on all of it, and if it's something
that can't heal or that's significant injury that you've really broken blood
vessels and blood is collecting, then even a part of it it
should be a problem. אלא לא שנא, ela lo shna, so it
doesn't matter, it's it's all one or it's all the other, it
shouldn't matter. So רש"י Rashi says which way does it not matter?
So רש"י Rashi says well, it sounds like from the beginning and
it sounds like based on other גמרות that it doesn't matter and
it's כשרה kesheira. either way. That's what רש"י Rashi is inclined to
do. תוספות Tosafos quotes the position of רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam and
actually says that no, either way it's טרפה. treifa. Now we're actually
going to find this later that the number of places where רש"י
Rashi, ruled an animal is כשרה, kesheira his grandson רבינו תם Rabbeinu
Tam ruled that it's טרפה. treifa. Also interestingly, apparently רבינו תם Rabbeinu
Tam wrote a book on טרפות treifos called הלכות גדולות. Hilchos Gedolos.
If you take a look on the תוספות Tosafos which is
אלא לא שנא, ela lo shna, it's a line that starts with
the word גרשום, Gershom, actually וכן משמע מתוך הלכות טרפות דרבינו גרשום,
v'chein mashma mi-toch Hilchos Treifos de-Rabbeinu Gershom,
that it seems this way from the הלכות טרפות Hilchos Treifos of
רבינו גרשום, Rabbeinu Gershom, it's interesting, everybody wrote these books on כשרות,
kashrus, handbooks on כשרות kashrus were like a major
industry, so already going back to רבינו גרשום, Rabbeinu Gershom, so it
seems that way. ובהלכות גדולות של רבינו תם, u-ve-Hilchos Gedolos shel Rabbeinu
Tam, ובקונטרס פירש
לשבח.
u-ve-kuntres
peireish le-shvach. Alright, first תוספות quotes those that say that it's טרפה,
treifa, it doesn't matter and it's טרפה treifa either way. And then
he says רבינו תם's Rabbeinu Tam הלכות גדולות Hilchos Gedolos and רש"י,
so here actually רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam agreed with his grandson, both
say that it's כשרה. kosher. We'll see him a little bit where
רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam disagrees with his grandson, but here he says
it's כשרה keshera, and interestingly quotes a book called הלכות גדולות Hilchos
Gedolos of רבינו תם. Rabbeinu Tam. Okay, so now the גמרא continues.
אלא לא שנא. ela lo shna. ואמר רבא, ve-amar Rava, and רבא
Rava also said, ריאה שיבשה מקצתה טרפה, reia she-yavsha miktzata treifa, if
a part of it got dried out, like if you open it
up and you see that it's hardened and dry and it's not
moist, but that's a part of the lung and not the whole
lung, it's still
כשרה. kasher. Excuse me, I misread that, it's יבשה מקצתה טרפה, yavsha
miktzata treifa, excuse me, if part of it got dried out it
is טרפה, treifa, it is a טרפה treifa even if part of
it got dried out. וכמה, ve-chama, and how much is considered to
be dried to be a problem? אמר רב פפא משמיה דרבא כדי
שתפרך בציפורן, amar Rav Papa mishmeih de-Rava kedei she-tiparech be-tziporen, so dry
that if you were to snap it with your finger it would
like crumble, it's so brittle. That's pretty darn brittle. So the גמרא
says כמאן, ke-man, who is that go like? כרבי יוסי בן המשולם,
ke-Rabbi Yossi ben ha-Meshullam, like Rabbi Yossi ben ha-Meshullam because we have
a similar debate by a בכור, bechor, you know, a firstborn you
want to... of a cow or sheep you want to know what
a מום mum is that you don't have to give it to
the כהן Kohen that you don't have to bring it as a
קרבן Korban that the כהן Kohen can eat it outside of the
בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. You still have to give it to the
כהן Kohen but it doesn't have to be brought as a קרבן.
Korban. What's a מום? mum? And one of them is if a
limb or particularly they speak about the ear is dried, is יבש.
yavesh. So how dried is dried? So let's take a look. דתניא,
Detanya, we taught in a ברייתא, איזהו יבשה? Eizehu yeveshah? What, how
dry is dry? שנתנקב ואינו מוציא טיפת דם, Shenitnakev v'eino motzi tipat
dam, so dried that there's no blood running through it anymore. If
you made a, made a hole in it with a pin, no
blood would come out. Okay, that you can understand. רבי יוסי בן
המשולם Rabbi Yossi ben HaMeshullam אומר, no no no it has to
be even worse. יבשה כדי שתהא נפרכת בציפורן, Yeveshah kedei shetehei niphrechet
betziporen, it would crumble with your fingernail if you snapped at it
it would crumble. So the גמרא assumes at least initially that dry
is dry and you use one definition to another. Of course it's
a big difference, one is about מום, mum, the other is not.
But presumably the issue here about מום mum is dried is a
מום mum already. The question about how dried is whether it will
be able to heal, whether it is a מום עובר mum over
or not a מום עובר, mum over, whether it is a temporary
or not temporary. So now we understand why the גמרא can compare
the two cases. Because if it's less than a certain threshold it
will heal, so if that's true about the ear, presumably it's true
also about the lung. So you're telling me that it has to
be able to crumble, anything less than that presumably will heal, so
that's going like this רבי יוסי ברבי משולם. Rabbi Yossi berabi Meshullam.
So the גמרא says, let's see what the גמרא says. אמרי, אפילו
תימא רבנן, Aphilu teima Rabbanan, no
it could even be the רבנן, Rabbanan, even the רבנן Rabbanan over
there that say that it won't heal after no blood can come
out, here they would wait till it could crumble. Why? גבי אוזן
בכור דקא שליט ביה זיקא, Gabei ozen bechor d'ka shalit bei zika,
by the ear which is exposed to the
air, so it's more susceptible. So there לא הדרא בריא, lo hadra
bari, once no blood is running through it, it will not heal
again. אבל ריאה דלא קא שליט בה אוירא, Aval reia d'lo ka
shalit bah avira, it's protected by the body and it's not exposed
to the air, so there הדרא בריא, hadra bari, even if no
blood comes out when you pinprick it,
it can still heal as long as it is not, it won't
crumble by being snapped when you snap at it. Okay, so that
is another problem about the lungs. So we've had a problem about
the hole, we spoke the hole has to go all the way
through, we spoke about how you can test it to see if
air bubbles come out with water or with feathers or whatever, so
that's going to be an important test. And now we've also spoken
about wounds and broken blood vessels and about being dried out. And
being dried is a problem if it's significantly dried.
Yes, so it doesn't speak about how much. It said מקצתה. miktzata.
So מקצתה miktzata presumably means even the smallest amount. Okay, and now,
now we're going to talk about, now we're going to get into
the real central issue about the adhesions. So let's take a look.
ואמר רבא, V'amar Rava, Rava also said, האי ריאה דקיימא גילדי גילדי
ואוכמי אוכמי, Hai reia dekaima gildi gildi v'uchmi uchmi, excuse me, we
have one more thing before the adhesions. If the lung looks like
peels peels, meaning like it's got like, it looks like different places,
it's like, it looks like sections have been peeled or whatever and
there's all these different spaces places where it looks
like flaky skin essentially in all these different places. או אוכמי אוכמי,
O uchmi uchmi, or black spots in different places. חזותא חזותא, Chazusa
chazusa, or other types of color. כשרה, it's still כשרה. Now we're
going to see a later גמרא that's going to talk about other
types of discoloration that's a problem, but and the ראשונים distinguish between
different types of discolorations, but at least this type of coloration we're
saying is okay. Okay, so let's take a look.
So that's discolorations. And now finally, okay, oops, no I keep on,
I'm too anxious to get to the, to get to the adhesions.
One more case. אמר מר אמר אמימר משמיה דרבא. Amar Mar Amar
Amimar mishme d'Rava. So אמימר Amimar said in the name of רבא,
Rava, אין מקיפין בבועי. Ein makiphin b'buei. You do not compare when
it comes to בבועי. b'buei. בבואי, buei, a בבואי buei is like
a type
of
a bump or which a, שפי שפרחא
בבועי.
Shepi
sheparcha
babuei.
Right, exactly. What's a good word for that?
Blister, what?
Blister? Well blister, isn't blister specifically as a result of like, a
blister is a specific type of it, maybe, but some type of
right, of like of a bump that's grown as a reaction to
something. So what? Boils? Boils, whatever, something like that. Now, the point
is like this, is that if you've got a, if you have
a question if the lung got a hole in it from before
שחיטה shechita or after שחיטה, shechita, maybe it got a hole as
a result of handling, one way of testing is by comparing to
a different sort of hole, you know, to another hole in a
different space in the lung. Like let's say you have another space
where you know it got the hole, you know, as a result
of handling. If you hold them next to each other, you know,
you could do a little comparison test. The גמרא will talk about
that later. So here what he's saying is that that comparison test
doesn't work if it's in an area where there are these blisters,
because the blisters will, you know, make it impossible to compare, and
it looks different and it appears different there than it appears in
other places. So if there is a doubt in this blister area
whether it got the hole before or after, you have to assume
that it got it after, there's no way of testing for it.
All right, we'll see more about the blisters and that testing later.
Now finally, hop, we're done. So we will have to hold off
till our—I'm so eager to get to the סירכות, sirchas, but we're
going to have to hold off for that for tomorrow. So to
be continued, same time tomorrow. Dov, you'll call me at this number,
right?